SEAN WELLECK: Today,
I'm excited to talk
about bridging informal and
formal mathematical reasoning
with AI.
So probably throughout
this course,
you've seen many
different ways where
these AI agents can start
to have a lot of impact
in different areas.
And so one interesting
question is to what extent
can they impact
more expert domains,
so, say, finance,
science, medicine,
and the domain that
I'll talk about today,
which is mathematics.
Now, with mathematics,
there's a variety of things
that you could imagine doing
with an agent or a language
model.
You could try to have
an open-ended dialogue
with the model.
You could try to have it come
up with counterexamples for you,
help you write proofs.
Your imagination is
basically the limit.
And what I want
to argue today is
that for math in
particular, how you
represent the math is actually
extremely important to think
about.
So one way to
represent math is what
is called informal mathematics.
Here, math is
represented as raw data.
So it could be text.
It could be an image.
It could be even audio,
if you're talking
with someone about math.
And doing this is
extremely flexible.
And in some sense, most of the
math that you've encountered
or that you've used is probably
in some kind of informal format.
So even something like a latex
solution or an archive paper,
we would consider
to be informal.
Now, when we think about using
AI to generate or operate
in informal math, there is
a really important problem,
which is that we don't have
any guarantees that the math is
correct or not.
So here is an
example of a language
model producing a solution.
And the answer at the
end is actually correct.
But makes these subtle mistakes
in the intermediate steps.
And so for really
simple math, this
might not actually be an issue.
And the language model
might still be useful.
But if we really want to
trust it in, say, education,
or in research
level math, then it
could get very tedious
and very difficult
to know whether the
outputs are correct or not.
So this motivates the other
end of the spectrum, which
is called formal mathematics.
Here, math is written as source
code in a programming language.
And basically, the
way it works is
you can write a specification
or a lemma or theorem, like,
1 plus 1 equals 2, then
you can write a proof.
And the really cool thing
is that if all of the code
compiles, then you have a formal
guarantee that the proof is
correct.
And so this is a lot different
than the informal math
because now we
can have certainty
if, say, a language model
generates a proof, that it
is actually a reliable and
correct proof of the theorem.
And there's been a variety
of these theorem proving
languages developed.
I'll mostly focus on a
language called Lean,
which recently is having
a really exciting growth
and really exciting intersection
with the mathematical community,
which I'll talk about in a bit.
And for one of the topics
that I'll talk about,
I'll also mention this
language called Isabelle
because it has
some features that
make it kind of
amenable to writing
different types of
proofs with AI systems.
So if you haven't seen
one of these before,
I wanted to actually show you
what one of these formal proof
assistants looked like.
And so to do this, we'll try
to prove this really simple
theorem, which is transitivity.
So if R is a subset of S
and S is a subset of T,
then R is a subset of T.
So I'll actually show
you this as a demo.
And so here what I've done
is I've opened up VS Code.
And so as I mentioned, this
is literally like programming,
like writing code.
And here you could see
the theorem statement.
So if R is a subset of S
and S is a subset of T,
then R is a subset of
T. And these are often
called interactive
proof assistants
because what happens is,
as I go to write a proof,
it actually tells me
over here, what is
the current state of the proof.
So the idea isn't to learn
every bit of the formal system.
But I'm just showing you
the important parts that
will be relevant for the talk.
So here we can see these
different variables.
And we can see what we have
remaining to prove over here.
Now the thing is that it takes
some expertise to actually write
a proof in Lean.
So for example, if I know some
Lean, then one thing I can do
is this command here.
And you can notice
that it actually
changed the state of the proof.
So now I have these
two variables up here.
And the goal has also changed.
Then again, if you
have some expertise,
then you can actually know
that this idea of transitivity
has already been
programmed into Lean.
So here I wrote this
transitivity rule here or lemma.
And now you can see
up here that it says
that there's no goals left.
So I've completed the proof.
So we'll actually touch
on a lot of things
that I've talked about
here throughout the talk.
We'll talk about the fact that
it requires some expertise
to actually write a proof in
one of these proof assistants.
And if you look
at this proof, it
might look a bit
different than one
that you would see
written down in a textbook
or something like that.
So we'll revisit these
ideas throughout the talk.
So now, going back
to the talk, we
could ask, like, OK, I showed
you this very simple example.
But is this toy or is
this actually useful
for more complex mathematics?
So a really exciting thing is
that, increasingly, there's
a larger and larger intersection
with the mathematical community.
So here's an example of the
mathematician Terence Tao.
And he formalized, in Lean,
the proof of a theorem from one
of his actual papers.
And a really exciting thing
that's playing into this
is this project, which
is called Mathlib.
So if you noticed, in the demo I
gave, this idea of transitivity
was already kind
of programmed in.
And that's the idea of Mathlib.
So lots of people are
contributing and building up
foundations that
other people can
use to make it easier to write
more and more complex math.
And if you look at what
mathematicians write or talk
to them and listen
to what they say,
then these formal
proof assistants
are exciting for a
few different reasons.
So one is that they
can potentially enable
a new form of collaboration.
So what you can do
is you can break down
a big problem or big proof
into multiple pieces.
And then anyone can
go on and essentially
submit code to try to
solve one of the pieces
to, say, prove one of the helper
theorems or helper lemmas.
And then the cool thing
is that we know for a fact
that we can trust the code
since Lean will automatically
check it.
And so this is a lot
different than the typical way
of collaborating on,
say, a math paper,
where you have to
trust the author
or read through their results.
It also gives you instant
feedback, as we saw.
So this could be useful in
a variety of ways, including
when trying to learn math.
And, of course, it has these
guarantees on correctness.
So, hopefully,
I've convinced you
that formal math is
getting more and more
interesting for learning or
for the actual mathematical
community.
But why is it actually
important for AI?
Well, one thing is
that, as we all know,
we are not able to
automatically check or trust
the outputs of AI models.
And so what the
formal system gives us
is some way of just
preventing incorrect math.
Or it turns out, you can
actually use this for code
as well.
Increasingly, we see more
and more models trained
with reinforcement learning.
And I'll actually talk about
one of those in the talk.
And what you can think of
the formal system as being is
it gives you this
perfect reward signal
of whether something is
correct or not correct.
And this turns out to
be very useful for then
improving machine
learning models further.
It also gets at one of the
hot topics in the field
right now, which is reasoning.
And it gives you
this nice playground
where you can try even very
easy reasoning problems to,
essentially, arbitrarily, hard
ones within the domain of math.
And so if we look at the
history of language models
in formal math, one of
the pioneering works
happened in 2020 from these
two authors from OpenAI.
And they developed a
system called gpt-f.
And so it actually
used a language model
to predict the next
steps of these proofs.
And even back then, they got
some pretty interesting results.
So what they did is they had
the system generate a proof,
and then they submitted
it as a pull request.
And here are some of the
comments from the maintainers
of the formal proof library.
Even this model, back then,
could produce shorter proofs.
And some of them were even
philosophically more concise
than the human-written ones.
And then since then,
we've seen rapid progress
in using methods based
on language models
for formal theorem proving.
So here is showing
the performance
on a really common benchmark.
These are based on math
competition problems.
And I actually made this
plot a few months ago.
But it's already out of date.
Actually, just
this morning, there
was a model released that
gets 80% on this benchmark.
And just to give you some
flavor of what these look like,
again, you don't have to read
through the details of this
or through most of the
examples I show in this talk.
But here's an actual output from
a model called DeepSeek Prover.
And it managed to produce
this proof of an IMO problem.
And so, hopefully, it
gives you some sense
that the outputs of
these are starting
to get pretty non-trivial.
And Terence Tao, if
we go back to members
of the mathematical
community, wrote
that during his
formalization project,
he was actually
using GitHub Copilot,
and sometimes it was able to
infer the directions he was
going in and things like that.
So with all this, with
formal math being so exciting
for both mathematics and
for AI, the question is,
why don't people in AI
always use formal math?
What is the blocker
to making this happen?
So I want to argue that the
key challenge is that there's
this gap between how people
are familiar with doing math
and the actual formal system.
In particular, there's just
so many ideas and intuitions,
and even the way
that we write proofs,
that are just difficult
or very tedious to express
in the formal system.
In a formal system like
Lean, each step of reasoning
needs to be explicitly
spelled out in detail.
And as we saw even in that very
simple example that I gave,
you often have to have a
deep knowledge of the system,
like what things
exist in the system,
and how to write
the code, and so on.
And so the theme
of this talk will
be steps towards bridging the
gap between informal reasoning
and formal reasoning.
Can we use AI and
language models
to get the best of
both worlds, maintain
the flexibility of
informal reasoning
while having all
of these benefits
that I mentioned with
operating in the formal system?
And so I'll talk about
three different directions
that we and others in the
community are pursuing.
First, I'll talk about
incorporating informal thoughts
into the formal theorem
proving procedure.
I'll talk about training
models to think informally
with reinforcement learning, and
in particular, our recent work,
which is called Lean-STaR.
Then I'll move to informal
provers or informal proofs.
And I'll talk about
how you can break down
the problem of writing
one of these proofs
as first writing a sketch, and
then filling in the lower level
gaps of the sketch.
So I'll talk about our work
called Draft-Sketch-Prove,
and then our recent work, which
is actually not even released
yet, of trying to
enable tools that
let you fill in the gaps of
these sketches in the Lean
Theorem Prover.
And then finally, at
the end of the talk,
I will talk about more
of a future direction
that we are taking
initial steps towards,
which is, how do
we actually make
these systems useful
to mathematicians
doing research
level mathematics.
So in particular, I'll
talk about one way
in which the models could
assist in these larger projects.
I'll talk about some tools
that actually already exist.
And you can try, after
the talk, if you want,
and a new benchmark that tries
to further progress of building
these assistants for these
complex, research level type
projects.
So with that, let me
go to the first part
where I will talk about
integrating informal thoughts
into formal theorem proving.
So here, this will
largely be based
on our paper called
Lean-STaR, which we'll
be presenting soon at ICLR.
And here, again,
we're in the setting
of theorem proving in Lean.
So here we have the theorem that
I showed you before at the top.
And then as I showed
you in the demo,
you could think
of this as a kind
of interactive
step-by-step process.
So in particular, Lean will give
you this state of the proof.
And then one thing
that you could do
is you could send that
state to a language model,
and it could try to generate
the next step of the proof.
Then you can provide
the next step to Lean.
And it can either tell you
whether the proof is done,
whether there is an
error, or, as we saw it,
it can give you the
next state of the proof.
You could then continue this
until you either give up
or you reach a complete proof.
And so in that sense, you
can see one of these proofs
as being a sequence of
states and next steps,
or they're called tactics.
So in a bit more detail,
what we want to do
is train a model on some data
set of inputs and outputs.
So an example is you could have
the model take in the proof
state and output the next step.
And what you typically
do is you extract
a lot of these state
and next step examples
from some corpus of
theorems and proofs.
So for example, you could use
the entire Mathlib project
that I mentioned earlier.
Or you could even have a model
generate its own theorems
and generate its own proofs.
And then, ultimately, you
turn it into a data set.
Once you've trained
a model, you then
want to use it to
generate full proofs.
So the traditional
way of doing this
is through this tree
search procedure.
Here's an example tree search
called best-first search.
And basically, the idea
is you ask the model
to generate multiple
candidates for the next step.
Then you somehow
come up with a score
for each one of
these candidates.
You choose the step
with the highest score.
So for instance, first, we
chose this intro h step.
Then you can expand
those further.
Choose the next highest
scoring sequence.
As you can see here,
it kind of backtracked.
And then it took
this green path,
which led to a correct proof.
So this is just one
possible strategy
you could use for generating
a full proof if your model can
only predict the next step.
So what we are
interested in is, can we
go beyond just training
the model on formal proofs,
and to generate formal
proofs, and instead
train the model to think before
each step of the formal proof?
So in particular, we
want to train the model
to generate what's on the right,
where before taking a step,
it outputs some reasoning.
And it's free to
decide whatever it
wants to do with the reasoning.
It could break down the problem.
It could plan out the next step.
It could even solve
some computation
that isn't really present
in the formal proof.
So why would you
want to do this?
Well, again, it
could give the model
some room to plan out
what it is about to do.
When you think about it, it can
help diversify the search space,
since now the model is
searching for proofs not
just in the formal space, but
in the formal space augmented
with these thoughts.
And I won't go
into details here.
But there's been a lot of cool
work in the language model
community showing that adding
in these chain of thought
in other domains can
actually give a model which
is more expressive in terms
of the kinds of problems
it can solve.
So we have a few good
reasons to try this out.
Now, the key issue here is
that nowhere on the internet
is there formal
proofs written in Lean
that have these nice thoughts
written out for them.
And so what we have to do is
actually design an algorithm so
that a model learns on its own
to produce these thoughts that
are useful for the proofs.
So the algorithm is
called Lean-STaR.
And it adopts its name
from this other work
called self-taught reasoner.
And the process basically
has two different phases.
So the high-level
idea is we want
to learn to generate these
thoughts via reinforcement
learning.
So first, we have to initialize
the model so that it can
produce some type of thoughts.
And then we want to train it
further so that it gets better
at using the thoughts
to prove theorems.
So in the first step we
use this clever trick,
which is we can look at a
state and the actual next step
of the proof, and then
have a language model just
retrospectively come up
with some thought that
describes the transition from
the state to the next step.
So what we found is that if
you don't give this step,
then the language
model might just
output a meaningless
or incorrect thought.
But they were good
enough at coming up
with some thought which
described this transition.
So then we can annotate
a large set of proofs.
So here, for instance,
we take all of Mathlib,
and we can get
hundreds of thousands
of examples of state
thought and next step.
Then we can use that
to train a model.
And it doesn't necessarily have
to use all 100,000, by the way,
for this initial step.
You want to just train
some initial model that
knows to produce these
thoughts prior to taking steps.
Then we want to take that model
and put it into this loop.
So we have the model
generate full proofs.
Then we ask Lean to tell us
whether they are correct or not.
And then we use some type of
reinforcement learning algorithm
to improve the model further.
So what we need is some
method to generate proofs.
And we need to actually
choose some algorithm
to implement this with.
So what we discovered is
that this commonly used way
of using the tree search,
or best first search,
was actually difficult
to get to work when
we added in these thoughts.
I think one reason
is that it gets
difficult to actually
assign a really
good score to the thought.
And so as a result, the tree
search didn't work as well.
So what we did is
design a new method,
which is this simple
idea of generating
multiple proofs in parallel.
So for a given trajectory,
you generate a step.
If you get an error
from Lean, you just
retry on that same path.
And then you keep going up
to a maximum number of steps,
or you stop if you
reach a complete proof.
Then for the algorithm, we
actually just used the simplest
possible algorithm.
And so we, as well
as other groups,
are now exploring
better reinforcement
learning algorithms,
like online algorithms.
But here we did
something very simple,
which is you just collect
the successful trajectories.
You add those to your data set.
And then you train a new model
on this data set of states,
thoughts, and tactics.
So this algorithm
goes by various names.
It's called expert iteration.
It's also called ReST-EM.
It's also called
rejection fine-tuning.
But the idea is very simple.
So then, typically, the way
that these models are evaluated
is on these math
competition problems.
So although we train
the model on Mathlib,
here's a common test
data set which is used,
which is called miniF2F.
And here's an example problem
from the International Math
Olympiad.
So here I've shown
the informal version,
just to show you what
the problem is like.
But then the model here
only gets the formal version
and has to produce a proof.
So here are some results
with an early model
that we tried in the project.
So in red, you can see the
model that we started with.
And then in black, you
could see the model
after we perform this
initialization step.
Then in gray, we
can see the model
after we perform the
expert iteration.
And you can see that the
Lean-STaR process basically took
it from being worse than
this baseline model, which
was based on this GPT-4 agent,
to being better than it.
Then at the end
of the project, we
applied Lean-STaR to the
best available base model
at the time for theorem proving.
And again, we saw
these improvements
going from gray to black.
And at the time
that we did this,
this was the state-of-the-art
for this miniF2F data set.
One really interesting
thing is that we
found that models
with the thoughts
benefit more from scaling
up the search budget,
or the inference budget.
So here we're seeing, as we
sample more and more steps,
either with our sampling
method, or as a baseline
with the best first search,
how the performance looks.
And you can see that the gains
we get from the green line,
which is Lean-STaR
with the thoughts,
are more pronounced
than the model that
doesn't have the thoughts.
And so this might be
indicating the idea
that I mentioned before,
that adding in these thoughts
helps to diversify
the search space.
Here are some examples.
And again, you don't have
to read through the details.
But if you're curious, you can
take a look at the paper after.
One interesting thing
here is that if you
look at the formal code, there's
actually some steps of reasoning
that the model is doing in the
informal thought, shown in gray,
that aren't really present
in the formal code.
And here's a longer
example, partly because it
looks impressive, but
also to just show you
that when you add in
these informal thoughts
with the formal ones,
the output starts
to get fairly non-trivial.
So after Lean-STaR, the
really exciting thing
is that this idea of
augmenting models or reasoning
models with thoughts and
training them with reinforcement
learning has been adopted in
the theorem proving community.
So in particular, very
rapidly, this idea
of incorporating
thoughts became a part
of the state of the art systems.
So here's the example that
I mentioned before called
DeepSeek Prover,
where they incorporate
in the informal thoughts.
And then as I mentioned
just this morning,
there was the state-of-the-art
prover released by this startup.
And you can see that
they have this idea
of alternating between informal
reasoning and snippets of code.
And then more broadly,
these reasoning models
that generate long
chains of thought
and are trained with
reinforcement learning
have really begun to
revolutionize the LLM reasoning.
So I'm not going to go
into the details here.
But you have probably heard
of these models like OpenAI 01
and DeepSeek R1.
And so it seems like,
at least currently,
having this kind of
informal thinking
is a really key part of
the reasoning procedure.
So to recap, Lean-STaR
builds on this observation
that training only
on the formal code
may be insufficient to learn the
actual thought process that's
needed to produce the code.
And it gives a simple
algorithm for learning
to generate the thoughts.
Now I'll move from
informal thoughts
to informal provers
and informal proofs,
and in particular, talk
about methods that prove
theorems by producing
this high-level sketch
and then filling in
the gaps of the sketch.
So here, the motivation
is to combine
the benefits of higher level
reasoning and lower level
reasoning.
And one motivation
for this is to think
about, how do we
actually write one
of these formal proofs in the
formal proof assistant-- sorry,
informal proofs in the
formal proof assistant.
So again, you don't
have to worry too much
about the details of this.
But here we're trying to prove
the statement on the left.
And what is notable here
is that we can somewhat
break this informal
proof up into these three
different parts.
Then it turns out
that we can write
this in the formal
system using something
that is structured analogously
to the informal proof.
So this is a system
called Isabelle.
And it has this
style where you can
write these intermediate
claims or conjectures.
And if you look at
it, they somewhat
line up with the
different steps.
Here, you have 10
times 280 divided
by 40, which shows up here.
And then this is a way
of basically writing,
OK, let's complete the proof.
Now, the interesting thing
here is that you still
need to produce a proof of one
of each one of these higher
level steps.
So that is shown in green.
And so you can see here
that to actually come up
with that proof,
it doesn't really
look like natural
language at all.
Here, it's actually
calling this SMT solver
and feeding it some facts.
So interestingly, we have this
decomposition between high-level
and these lower level things.
So let me actually say
a bit more about how
you produce these
lower level proofs
in a system like Isabelle.
So it turns out that there are
these very powerful and very
useful automation
tools called hammers,
or this one is
called Sledgehammer.
And the basic idea
is that as you're
writing a proof as
a human, you could
write one of these
conjectures, and then you
could call the Sledgehammer.
What it does under the
covers is it calls out
to external automated
provers, ones
that are based on first
order logic or higher order
logic or SMT solvers.
And these turn out to
be extremely effective
when you're using the
system for filling
in these little
gaps of the proof.
What these are not
good at is, let's say
you want to solve
an IMO problem,
then the Sledgehammer
methods just won't succeed.
The technical reason is that
based on how they're set up,
there is just such a large
search space of possible proofs.
And in particular, if you
think about this proof
as being structured as
these have statements,
they don't really
have the functionality
to produce statements like that.
So in practice, these
are used interactively
as you're writing
a proof as a human.
So here, the idea is
we want to combine
some kind of high-level
prover with a lower level
prover like the Sledgehammer.
And this leads to
our method, which
is called
Draft-Sketch-Prove, which
we presented in ICLR in 2023
and developed and released
in late 2022.
So here, the idea is to come up
with this three step procedure.
First, we're going to
draft an informal proof.
Then we're going to translate
it into this formal sketch.
And then we're going to use
a low-level prover to fill
in the gaps of the sketch.
So to show you this
in more detail,
let's walk through
each one of these.
So first we start off
with an informal theorem
and a formal theorem statement.
It's actually really important
to provide the system
with the formal
theorem statement
because when we start
to translate things,
we want to make sure that
the model's not cheating,
and it's actually proving the
thing that we want it to prove.
Then in the first step,
we have the system--
so it could be a human
or it could be an LLM--
generate some informal proof.
Then in the next step we have an
LLM translate the informal proof
into what's called
a formal sketch.
It's essentially what I showed
you before, except now, we
leave these gaps to be filled,
which are the lower level
proofs.
Then in the final stage,
we try to close the gap
with a lower level prover.
Here, we are actually
using the Sledgehammer tool
that I told you about.
And if you're able to
close all of the gaps,
then you're guaranteed
to have a complete proof.
The interesting thing
is that this actually
looks a lot different than
what I was showing you before,
where we have this
step-by-step proof search,
and maybe it's a tree search.
Now what we can do is we can
diversify the search space
by just generating many possible
informal proofs or drafts,
and/or generate many potential
translations of those
into formal sketches.
And then we can just
try to fill in the gaps.
And if the gaps are filled
in any of the sketches,
then we have a formal proof
that we could consider
as the output of the system.
So here's showing what
happens as we scale up
the number of calls
to the pipeline.
So here we're either generating
many informal proof drafts,
or in the case of using a
human written informal proof,
we're generating many
possible translations
into the formal sketch.
You can see on the left-hand
side that if we just call
the system once,
then it actually--
I mean, it proves some things,
but it's not very good.
And we really see the benefits
as we scale up the amount
of proof search or sampling.
And up here, we're proving
a large number of problems.
This is on the same
miniF2F data set.
Now, this was in the days
of Codex and Minerva,
if you remember those models.
And interestingly here,
if you look on the very
right-hand side, if we actually
sampled enough from the model,
then we were able
to, right at the end,
surpass the performance of
using a human-written proof.
And so this was
kind of exciting.
And probably, now that language
models are much better,
we would be able to make
that transition even earlier.
So here's an example of proving
an International Math Olympiad
problem.
So here the language model
produces the informal proof,
shown in green.
Then the language model
produces the formal sketch,
shown in blue.
You can see that here,
we actually, back then,
even had these informal
thoughts in as comments.
Or here, it's showing the
informal version of the setup.
And then we have the
Sledgehammer system fill
in the gaps, shown in purple.
And you can see that sometimes
it's pretty non-trivial.
Here, again, it's
calling this SMT solver
and feeding in a bunch of
different facts or premises.
So since then, I've put together
a tutorial for theorem proving.
So it goes over the
step-by-step methods
that I mentioned
in the first part,
and also has a notebook that
shows you how to implement
this Draft-Sketch-Prove method.
And in particular, it just calls
out to a language model API.
So you can try it out with any
state-of-the-art model that you
want to, if you're
curious to learn more.
So to recap, I talked
about this method
called Draft-Sketch-Prove,
which generates
these high-level sketches, and
then tries to fill in the gaps.
And what this relied on is,
in this language, Isabelle,
having this lower level
prover called Sledgehammer.
So next, I'm going to talk about
our very recent work on trying
to build one of these
Sledgehammer provers
for Lean so that we
could more easily write
these sketch-based
proofs in Lean.
So this is based on a paper
that is still not public,
which is called Premise
Selection for a Lean Hammer,
where we build a system
called Lean Hammer.
So what is a hammer?
So a hammer integrates,
as I mentioned,
these external provers.
And there's a bit
of terminology here
that is a bit tricky
if you haven't
seen this distinction before.
Specifically, what it does is it
integrates an automated theorem
prover into an interactive
theorem prover.
So an interactive theorem
prover is like the one
I showed you, like Lean.
And essentially, it's a
programming language that
is able to check the proofs.
However, the
language, on its own,
doesn't give you a way of
automatically producing
the proofs.
You usually have to
write them as a human.
An automated theorem
prover is something
that tries to
automatically find proofs.
And traditionally,
these are based
on different kinds of logics.
So they might be based on higher
order logic provers or things
like SMT solvers.
And so as I mentioned before,
these automated theorem
provers really struggle
with more complex proofs
due to this large search
space in their formalism.
So what we can do to try
to help with this problem
is to solve this really
important problem, which
is called premise selection.
So basically, what you do is you
provide the automated theorem
prover with many
different facts.
So you can provide it with
definitions, different theorems,
different lemmas.
And then it goes off and
tries to prove the theorem
that you want.
And if we look at the
number of premises
in, say, Lean's Mathlib,
then it's extremely large.
So it's hundreds of
thousands of premises.
And so if you just give all of
those to the automated theorem
prover, it will really
struggle because it has
this really large search space.
So the basic idea
of premise selection
is to somehow cut down the
number of premises that we give
and only provide it ones
that are likely to be
useful for proving the theorem.
So then we can look at what is
the typical hammer pipeline.
So here it is at a high level.
Let's say we're in Lean.
Then we start off with the thing
we want to prove on the left.
Then we would pass it to some
kind of premise selection
system.
Now, once we've selected
premises like definitions
and theorems, we have to
translate it from Lean
into the language of the
automated theorem prover.
Let's say that the
automated theorem
prover finds a complete proof.
Well, then we have to
actually translate it back
into a Lean proof.
And so the way
that that's done is
through the step, which is
called proof reconstruction.
So it basically takes
the output and tries
to produce a proof in Lean.
Then as our output, we would see
this nice proof on the right.
Sorry.
So amazingly, there's been
a lot of really cool work
in the community on
these different parts.
Usually, they're developed
somewhat independently
of each other, but we have
this translation layer
called Lean-auto that
can help translate
from Lean's
dependent type theory
into the higher order logic.
An example automated
theorem prover
is called zipper position.
And then for this
proof reconstruction,
this was developed by Josh
Clune and collaborators,
who's part of this
Lean hammer project.
And there's a
system called Duper.
So what we're interested in
here is two different things.
First, we want to try to solve
this premise selection problem.
And then second,
we have to come up
with some way of actually
combining these together.
When I show it on
a slide it looks
simple to put them together.
But it's actually not clear
what the best way to do this is.
And even more, we want to go
beyond the standard pipeline,
which I'll talk about in a bit.
So first, let me talk about
the premise selection.
What we do is to frame
this as retrieval
with a neural language model.
So in particular, we have
a standard retrieval setup.
Here, we embed our input.
So this will be the goal
that we want to prove.
And we have a
language model that
produces this embedding
shown on the right.
Then we embed all of
our potential premises.
So this will include
theorems, definitions, lemmas.
And they could be from Mathlib.
They could also be local
premises in your project
or in the hypotheses that
you're going to prove.
And with that, we get
this list of embeddings
shown on the right.
Then to select the premises,
we take the dot product,
use cosine similarity to
select the set of highest
ranked premises.
So here, we train with this
contrastive loss that is often
used to train retrieval models.
So it boils down to collecting
these inputs, the states,
as well as some positive
premises and negative premises.
And it turns out that there's
actually a lot of nuance in how
to do this properly, especially
when the output is going to be
this Lean-auto--
sorry, when the interface is
with this Lean-auto system
in the hammer pipeline.
So I won't go into
all the details here.
And when we release the paper,
it will have all the details.
But even things like how and
whether you simplify terms,
how exactly you choose
these positive premises
and negative premises,
turn out to have
a large impact on the
behavior of the retriever.
And so we'll show in the
results in a second that
based on some previous
retrievers that were trained,
our system that we trained does
a lot better when we put it
into this hammer pipeline.
So then the question
is, how do we combine
all of these different pieces?
And so what we did is not
just have this linear picture
that I showed on
the previous slide,
but we actually incorporate
these components
into a tree search.
So there's a really
cool tree search method.
And it's this symbolic
tree search called Aesop.
It does this tree search over
different tactics or steps
of the proof.
And so what we do
is wire it up so
that it can use the
selected premises
to call different
tactics in Lean.
And it can, at any time, query
this automated theorem prover
using the selected premises.
And so this step will
involve the translation
that I mentioned, as well
as the proof reconstruction.
So now with all of
these different parts
that I've described,
you could say,
how is this actually
useful as a user?
Well, it turns out that we
can wrap this all into one
simple command.
So at any step of a
proof, you can just
call this hammer
tactic, and then it'll
run this tree search
that I mentioned,
call the external
prover and all that.
And then if it succeeds, it
will display the proof to you
on the right.
And what's cool about this
is you could potentially
enable this kind of
sketch-based proving
that I was talking about before.
So here, I want to show an
actual demo of the system
where we took a human-written
proof sketch from this textbook,
Mathematics and Lean.
And we want to try to fill in
the gaps with the hammer system.
So this theorem is
the irrationality
of the square root of two.
And yeah, sometimes
in the formal system,
you'll write it in a
slightly different way.
Yeah, the details are not
too important for the demo.
But you can read through
after if you want.
So here, we'll go
back into VS Code.
And here is, first of
all, the simple theorem
that I showed you before.
And so what we can do is
we can call this hammer.
And the first time you run
it should take a few seconds.
And so what it's done is
it's selected the premises
and called the tree
search and all that.
And now you can see
that it came back
with this proof, this
theorem, or lemma.
So this one just says
that if two divides m
squared then two will divide m.
So it turns out that
this one will actually
be useful in this
irrationality proof below.
So now we can go
step by step and try
to fill in the gaps
with the hammer.
So here it got this one.
And we can just keep going.
And interestingly,
up here, it actually
used the Lemma that
we just proved.
So you can see two divide
of two divide square.
And so here it succeeded again.
And I'll just keep
going for fun.
So the idea here is
that by doing this,
you don't necessarily
have to worry
about these different details.
So here's a kind
of interesting one
where it's actually calling
the automated theorem prover.
So you can see all of
the different facts that
are being passed to it.
And here, we could see the
call, the actual call to Duper.
So Duper was this proof
reconstruction method
that I mentioned before.
So if you want, you could
treat this as the proof,
or you can just leave
this one in there.
For this step,
turns out you have
to do this one step of
clearing out this hypothesis.
But then you can
call the hammer.
And just for fun, I'll
finish off this proof just
to show you that it's possible.
And then here's the last step.
And we can call the hammer.
OK, so now we have a complete
proof of the theorem.
And we started off with
these high-level steps
and were able to
fill in the gaps.
So again, here's the summary.
Then what we could
do is evaluate this
with different premise
selectors swapped in.
So here's some
results on theorems
that we held out from Mathlib
as a test set And we just
run the hammer at the
first step of the proof.
So on the left here,
you can see what
happens if you don't have
the premise selection.
Then here is using a retriever
that was from prior work.
What we did is we retrained
it on the exact same snapshot
of Mathlib so it
had up-to-date data.
And it's partially showing that
the specific decisions that we
make in training our retriever
were really important
for performance.
Interestingly, there's a
symbolic premise selection
system.
I believe it's based
on the one that
was in Isabelle Sledgehammer.
So Kim Morrison from
the Lean community
re-implemented it in Lean.
And you can see that it actually
does pretty decently when
it's in our hammer pipeline.
Here is the Lean
hammer retriever
as the fourth bar with
the diagonal lines.
And then interestingly,
it ends up
being complementary to the
symbolic MePO retriever.
So you can see with
these crosshatched lines,
you get a performance
boost if you just
take the union of premises.
And then in absolute terms, it's
starting to get pretty good.
So all the way on the
right is the performance
that we get if we just use
the ground truth premises that
occur in the human proof.
And you can see
that the performance
is starting to approach
the performance that we
get if we use those.
So to recap, I talked about
two different approaches
for combining informal
and formal provers or even
formal/informal proofs.
I talked about
Draft-Sketch-Prove,
which involves drafting
an informal proof,
generating a formal
sketch, and then filling
in the low-level details.
And I talked about
Lean hammer, which
is trying to bring this paradigm
to Lean or make it easier.
So in particular, we try
to build this hammer.
And it involves this neural
premise selection and a tree
search and calling out to
the automated theorem prover.
And one interesting
takeaway from this is--
I didn't go into the detail
of the model that we trained--
but the largest model that we
trained was just a 100 million
parameter retriever,
so very small.
And as you maybe
saw in the demo,
you can get some pretty
non-trivial behavior
or performance from
integrating it in.
So it's kind of exciting
because in these cases,
even these fairly small,
by today's standards,
neural networks can
be fairly powerful.
So in the last
part of the talk, I
want to talk about trying to
use AI or techniques that I've
talked about to actually assist
in research-level mathematics.
So not just prove
the IMO problems
but try to help out in
these more complex projects
that mathematicians, or
if you're a Lean hobbyist,
or interested in formalizing
something difficult.
So what does it
actually look like to
formalize research-level math?
Well, here we can look
at this blog post that
was written by Terence Tao.
And he breaks down
the steps that
were involved in formalizing
a proof from this paper, which
is shown on the left.
So again, the goal was to
take one of the main theorems
from the paper and then
try to write it in Lean
and come up with a formal proof.
And the first step is to write
what is called a blueprint.
So here you go step by
step and think about
how would this proof decompose
into different definitions,
into different lemmas.
And ultimately, we can come up
with the kind of final theorem
and proof that we care about.
And as you can see
here, on the top,
it's showing a dependency
graph of all of these theorems
and all of these definitions.
So it gets fairly complex.
And at the very bottom,
you have the final theorem
and final proof.
And so, interestingly
here, everything
is still written in
informal language.
So you could see here
the theorem and the proof
just written in LaTeX.
And then you try
to think about, OK,
how do we actually
realize this in Lean.
And so what it comes
down to is a large set
of these formal definitions
and formal lemmas
and formal theorems.
And then ultimately, you're
able to state your final theorem
and write the proof of it.
So at the end, you have
this proof and this theorem
that are really dependent
on this graph of things
that I showed you.
So a question is, at what point
of this procedure could AI help?
So maybe, at least
for now, we don't
have it do this whole
pipeline end to end.
But we could think about,
what is the simplest
thing that we could have it do
and that we could have trust.
So one thing you could do is
you could look at this blueprint
and look at just one of
these theorems or lemmas that
is necessary for the proof,
but is just one part of it.
So here's an example where
we have this lemma, which
occurs somewhere in here.
And if we give this
to a language model
and it produces a
proof, then, again, we
can trust the output
because Lean has checked it.
And in some sense, it's
helped the development,
because then the human
proof writer doesn't
have to go through this step.
So in order to do
this, we really
have to overcome at least two
different gaps that occur.
The first I'll call
the accessibility gap.
And this is just the simple
observation that a lot of times
these methods are
developed, but then they're
actually hard to integrate
into actual tools.
So for example, the system
might be very capable,
but it might not be open source.
Or the results might
be very impressive,
but then they're actually very
expensive or costly to run.
And so when you think about
this practical setting,
it adds constraints
onto the methods
that you have to develop.
But luckily, we actually do have
some tools already available
that could potentially be
useful for these simple gaps.
So we developed one of
them called LLM Lean.
You could go download it and
use it right now if you want.
So the basic idea
is to just create
this interface between Lean
and some language model.
So what it does is it gives
you these different commands
or tactics, like, this one
queries a language model
to try to produce the
next step of the proof.
And then we can actually check
the outputs of the model.
So we could discard the
incorrect ones and just
display ones that
finish the proof.
Those are shown in green.
Or blue ones are ones
that don't give an error,
but don't necessarily
finish the proof.
And in particular, you
can, even nowadays,
have a model running
on your laptop.
So there's these
different libraries
that have been developed
like Ollama or LM Studio.
And you could basically host a
language model on your laptop,
and then use LLM Lean
to communicate with it.
Similarly, you can have it
communicate with some API.
So it could be OpenAI, it could
be Claude, Gemini, together.ai.
And so now you can
actually try to use
these models to
give you suggestions
that are checked in Lean.
So as the last demo, I
wanted to just show you this.
And so let's look
for the other window.
So let's go back to this
really simple theorem
that I showed at the
beginning of the talk.
And you might have noticed that
I imported this LLM Lean here.
And so now we could call this
LLM step command that I showed.
And actually, it comes up
with this intro command
that I showed you at the
beginning of the talk.
Then we could call it again.
And in this case, it was
able to finish the proof.
So another thing
you can do is you
could say, try to just
do this exact command,
so try to prove it in one step.
It actually came up with this
bit more clever, one-step proof.
There's another
command that just
tries to prove it in
end-to-end, like, fully
prove it instead of just
predicting the next step.
So here, the model comes up
with multiple potential proofs.
And you can see they're a
bit different style, maybe,
a bit longer.
So you can also do other fun
things like shorten this proof,
then put it as a comment
and then call llmqed.
So let's see what it does.
And yeah, so now it gives us
some options that are shorter.
Actually, this is pretty short.
You could just prove
it in one call.
So yeah, this is a tool
that you could use.
Today, you just need to
have a language model API.
And then you can import
it into a Lean project.
So interestingly,
let's see here,
the methods are still
bottlenecked, obviously,
by how good the model
is at proving theorems.
But even now, I went through
Terence Tao's project, this PFR
project, and just picked a file.
Yeah, this one was
actually able to fill
in some of these small lemmas.
This was actually the
example that I showed you
before on the previous slide.
So another thing is, I mentioned
that the models right now are
the bottleneck.
We have the interface set up.
And so now it just comes
down to whether the model can
complete theorems that occur
in these kinds of projects.
So this leads to a second gap,
which is the gap in the way
that we benchmark these
theorem proving models.
So largely, these models are
benchmarked on their ability
to prove these math
competition problems,
like, ones from the IMO.
And what these problems have is
they're fairly self-contained.
So you can usually
state the problem
in just one line of code.
And then they're designed to
somewhat use standard results.
So there's a standard set.
And a lot of them have been
implemented in Mathlib.
And then constructing the
proof is very difficult.
It requires a lot of creativity.
But it's relying on
these standard results.
If we compare that
to this project
that I've been
telling you about,
these have these
complex dependencies
from throughout the project.
So in particular, this theorem,
to even state it or to prove it,
it might actually
rely on these brand
new definitions and brand
new lemmas that have
been created for the project.
And so unless we
continually train the model
on all of the current
projects, it really
has to learn to prove theorems
in this context-dependent
setting that I'm
showing on the right.
So this leads to our
new benchmark called
miniCTX, or mini context.
And we'll also be
presenting this at ICLR
as an oral presentation.
So here what we do is we made
this observation that I just
told you about that when we
look at these research-level or
actual formalizations
that people do in Lean,
they are really in this
context-dependent setting
where you want to
prove a theorem,
and it depends on a
whole repository of code,
new definitions, or
new auxiliary lemmas.
So the idea of the
benchmark is to test models
on actual real Lean projects.
So in particular, we
choose some date cutoff.
And then we look at a
project like Mathlib.
And we can take all
of the theorems that
were developed after that date.
Similarly, we can look at
when a project was created
and take theorems and contexts
from those different projects.
So this PFR project by
Terence Tao and collaborators
that I've been
telling you about is
one of the projects that
was in the first version
of this benchmark.
Then the idea is
we also make tools
so that you can automatically
extract benchmark problems
from these projects.
So what you can do is
update the benchmark
to stay ahead of the training
cutoffs for these language
models.
So we've actually already
released a miniCTX version 2.
And it has more
recent Lean projects
that have been developed in
the past couple of months.
So here, we have two
different types of contexts.
And these are basically
what dependencies
are needed to prove a theorem.
And what we do is we build
tooling to automatically extract
things like dependencies.
And we can look
at, does a theorem
depend on things just
in the current file
or does it depend on things
across multiple files.
And then we can also
get things like,
what are the set of
available premises
when you're going to
prove this theorem, so
a very realistic setting.
So in particular, let's look
at two different settings.
One setting is where
all of the dependencies
just appear in the current
file, and then the other
is when the dependencies
can span multiple files.
So the first thing we want
to do is actually demonstrate
that this context
actually matters.
So, again, I've told you
about this really common way
of training theorem
provers, which
is by just giving
them the proof state
and then having them
produce a next step,
or having them produce
thoughts if you want.
So here what we did is develop
this simple baseline method,
which additionally
gives the model all
of the code in the file so far.
So this can include new
definitions, new lemmas,
even new notation, or
natural language comments.
And we want to see how this
compared to just taking
in the proof state.
So interestingly, if you look at
a competition problem data set,
like, miniF2F, it actually
really doesn't matter.
You can do, pretty
similarly, whether you
take in additional
context, it would just
be the import
statements for miniF2F,
or if you just take
the proof state.
So this might be one reason why
a lot of these state-of-the-art
theorem proving methods don't
really deal with or support any
external context.
However, when we evaluate
them on our benchmark,
miniCTX, which has the theorems
from real-world projects,
we can see this dramatic
gap in the performance.
And the reason is pretty obvious
if you just look at a Lean file,
it's because in
these real projects,
you're defining these new
definitions and new lemmas
like I discussed.
Interestingly, you can also
do this premise selection
and give the language
model the premises.
And you can see variations based
on whether the theorem requires
just in-file information
or auto-file information.
So all the way on the
left, we have theorems
with very low dependencies.
The first set of bar graphs
shows high dependencies
on in-file premises.
And so here you could see
that you do pretty well
by just giving the
language model all
the code in the current file.
And then in the third
set of bar graphs,
you see what
happens when we have
these cross-file dependencies.
And you can see that adding
in this premise selection
leads to some improvement.
So here, we're using an older
premise selector system.
So we're excited about
integrating our Lean hammer
into this for addressing
the cross-file dependencies.
And in general,
there's a wide space
of methods that could be
developed for this setting.
So I should also mention that we
provide the model with this file
tuning.
So it's trained to take in the
file context through Ollama.
So you can download it,
run it on your laptop,
and use it inside of Lean.
And then all of the
methods that are
in LLM Lean that are calling
the proprietary language
models, or the API-based
ones, they'll actually
prompt the model with all of
the code in the current file.
And then as I mentioned,
everything from the project
is open source.
So the data, the models,
our data extraction tool,
and even the
evaluation code, which
is like a wrapper
of the Lean ripple.
And so you can check out
those resources online.
So as I mentioned
in the third part,
if we look at these
real Lean projects
or what it would take to
formalize research-level math,
it opens up some
unique challenges.
These aren't the only
challenges, of course,
but two that are really
present in the kind of research
community right now.
One is that we still have a
gap between the AI advances
and tools that people can use.
And then second, the
benchmarks don't always
reflect all of the
capabilities that
are required to do this
real-world formalization.
And so this is very much
an open research direction.
And as I mentioned, this
benchmark is the first step.
So in summary, in this
talk, I talked about three
different ways to try to
bridge informal and formal
mathematical reasoning.
I talked about incorporating
informal thoughts by training
models to think informally.
I talked about incorporating
informal provers
or informal proofs through
methods like sketch proofs,
and try to fill in the gaps.
And then towards
the end, I talked
about trying to take, say, a
research paper and look at what
is involved in producing
a formal version of it
and looking at what are
some initial ways where
AI can help in the process.
And so with that, that is
all I have for today's talk.
And I'd like to thank all
of the amazing collaborators
on these various works.
They're listed here.
And again, my name is Sean.
And I have my
email address here,
so please feel
free to reach out.